<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2041-1723</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6978510</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">14048</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-14048-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The systemic and governmental agendas in presidential attention to climate change in Mexico 1994&#x02013;2018</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Balderas Torres</surname><given-names>Arturo</given-names></name><address><email>arturo@cipad.mx</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lazaro Vargas</surname><given-names>Priscila</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5720-466X</contrib-id><name><surname>Paavola</surname><given-names>Jouni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8403</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9909.9</institution-id><institution>Centre for Climate Change Economics and Policy (CCCEP), School of Earth and Environment, </institution><institution>University of Leeds, </institution></institution-wrap>Leeds, LS2 9JT UK </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Centro de Investigaci&#x000f3;n y Proyectos en Ambiente y Desarrollo (CIPAD), CP 45050 Zapopan, Mexico </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0483 6569</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.466861.b</institution-id><institution>Environmental Engineering, </institution><institution>Instituto Tecnol&#x000f3;gico y de Estudios Superiores de Occidente (ITESO), </institution></institution-wrap>CP 45604 Tlaquepaque, Mexico </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>455</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Ambitious climate action requires sustained long-term attention from political leaders. To understand how climate change entered the political agenda in a developing country, we examine from an agenda-setting perspective the attention paid by Mexican presidents to this issue from 1994 to 2018. We perform a longitudinal analysis of 968 documents referring to climate change published by four presidencies to describe changes in attention levels over time and to determine how changes in international agreements and public policies (i.e. systemic agenda) and National Development Plans (NDPs)(i.e. governmental agenda) influence them. Our results indicate international agreements and national legislation establish a baseline for inclusion of climate change into governmental actions. Agenda changes driven by international agreements result in reactive changes in attention, while ambitious approaches are aligned with proactive NDPs. Our results also indicate public awareness and electoral periods can open windows of opportunity for reframing agendas and promoting ambitious climate action.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="web-summary"><p id="Par2">It is important to gain a better understanding on the contributing factors fostering climate action in developing countries. Here, the authors investigate the attention levels paid to this issue in the planning and implementation stages of climate policies in Mexico during 1994-2018, and find that international negotiations and executive governmental plans are strong drivers of the climate policy discourse in Mexico and likely to be so for developing countries more generally.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Climate-change policy</kwd><kwd>Government</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Funding details have been removed to comply with the double blind review process.</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Ambitious climate action requires that policy and decision-makers focus on the issue in the long term<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Agenda-setting studies seek to elucidate why some problems emerge and are included in the public agenda and policies (e.g. in refs. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>). Since individuals and institutions have a limited capacity for attention (e.g. in refs. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>), understanding how problems capture the leaders&#x02019; attention is critical<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> as the level of attention indicates the importance of an issue and has agenda-setting effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Our objective is to investigate from an agenda-setting viewpoint how the attention to climate change paid by Mexican presidents evolved from 1994 to 2018: in particular, we assess the effect of changes in the governmental and systemic or legal agendas on the level of attention.</p><p id="Par4">Interest in environmental issues, such as climate change rise and fall over time<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, but it is in periods of high interest when new institutions and policies to address them are adopted<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Policies and attention cycles can have long stable periods alongside short and intense periods of agenda and policy change, which can have long-lasting effects (i.e. punctutated equilibrium<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>). In his classic work Kingdon<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> proposed that three conditions need to be met for an issue to enter an agenda: a problem is recognized, solutions are available and political conditions are favorable. A window of opportunity arises when the three conditions are met and policy change can be promoted<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. The complementary punctuated equilibrium model suggests that changes in interests and policy processes are linked to changes in the definition of issues and relevant institutions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Earlier research has shown that attention to climate change is affected by new scientific information, feedback on implemented actions and focusing events<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Historically, developing countries had little interest in climate policy because economic development was seen to require industrialization and increased carbon emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Climate policy was thus not a priority for them and any interest in it was at first based on international consensus and only later on domestic support<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Following the negotiations under the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC) climate policy has spread from international to national and sub-national levels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. The attention paid to climate change is increasing both in international and national agendas<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. In developing countries, drivers of climate policy include international negotiations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>; potential access to international finance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>; reputation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>; interest in international decision making<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>; concerns about energy security and other local problems or co-benefits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>; the sense of responsibility<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>; and interest to divert external pressure for more ambitious action<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">Earlier research often focused on advances in international negotiations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> and its focus on developed countries has left processes occurring in the developing world underresearched. The failure to reach an agreement in Copenhagen in 2009<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> highlighted the role of emerging economies in climate change governance. Thereafter negotiations focused on inclusive long-term climate action which culminated six years later in Paris<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. But pledges made under the Paris Agreement (PA) remain insufficient to prevent dangerous climate change<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Therefore, it is important to understand how climate change can gain importance in the policy agendas in Non-Annex I developing countries, which now account for 50% of annual greenhouse gas emissions globally<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par7">We contribute to addressing this evidence gap by examining the attention given to climate change by Mexican presidents over a 24-year period of four federal administrations during which climate change became a policy issue globally and nationally in Mexico (1994&#x02013;2018). The administrations are those of Ernesto Zedillo Ponce de Le&#x000f3;n (EZPL), Vicente Fox Quesada (VFQ), Felipe Calder&#x000f3;n Hinojosa (FCH), and Enrique Pe&#x000f1;a Nieto (EPN). Our analysis covers three administrative changes and two changes in the political party in power. EZPL and EPN represented the Institutional Revolutionary Party (PRI), a centrist pragmatic party. VFQ and FCH are members of the National Action Party (PAN), a party close to conservative investors and private sector. Common to the four administrations is that they all implemented neoliberal economic policies (e.g. in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>) and that since 1997, their political parties did not have majority in the federal Congress (e.g. in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>). In presidential regimes such as that of Mexico, the leadership of the executive is critical in setting the priorities for public policies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par8">Following agenda-setting scholars, we consider that the political agenda consists of: first, the public agenda or the issues of interest to the general public; second, the systemic agenda of issues addressed by legislation, and; third, the governmental agenda of issues proactively and explicitly considered in public decision making<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. We perform a longitudinal study using content analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup> to build a chronology of attention. Our evidence base is the documents referring to climate change and published by the presidential offices over the 24-year period (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;968). We study how changes in the governmental and systemic agendas<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> relate to the changes in and patterns of presidential attention to climate change in Mexico.</p><p id="Par9">For our purposes, we define the systemic agenda as the policies and activities originating to international agreements and enacted domestic climate legislation, while the governmental agenda is defined in National Development Plans (NDPs)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. In Mexico, signed international agreements have a high legal status only just below the Constitution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. The NDPs in turn are mandatory legal instruments which guide public action and establish the priorities, objectives and programs of the administration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Development planning is not exclusive to Mexico: it has been common in many developing countries<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup> since the 1960s. Therefore, improved understanding of how NDPs as a key aspect of governmental agenda relate to climate policy and attention cycles has wider relevance.</p><p id="Par10">Few studies have analysed to date how NDPs address environmental issues (e.g. in refs. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>). We contribute new quantitative evidence from the analysis of a large data set on attention patterns, which is particularly novel in research on climate policy in non-Annex I countries.</p><p id="Par11">In what follows, we describe key developments in climate policy in Mexico before presenting the results of our analysis. Our findings indicate that changes in the governmental and international systemic agendas resulted in discernible changes in attention levels paid by Mexican presidents to climate change. We find that international agreements and domestic legislation provide a bottom line for addressing climate change, but that ambitious climate action is based on ambitious executive governmental plans.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Background on climate policy in Mexico</title><p id="Par12">Mexico provides a good case to understand climate action<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. Despite being a middle-income, non-Annex I country contributing &#x0003c;2% of the global GHG emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>, it was one of the first countries to adopt a voluntary mitigation target in 2008 and national climate legislation in 2012<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. To understand the evolution of Mexican climate action it is important to acknowledge that as a non-Annex I country to the UNFCCC it did not adopt a legally binding mitigation target under the Kyoto Protocol (KP). The Annex I was based on membership of the Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Develompent (OECD) at the time<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. The text of the UNFCCC was prepared in 1992 at the Rio Summit and ratified later in March 1994; Mexico joined the OECD only a few months later in May 1994. The country collaborated closely with the OECD since the early 1980s and the process to join it accelerated in 1993<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. By the time Mexico joined the OECD, it was the ninth largest economy in the group; yet on per capita income basis Mexico was at the bottom of the group just above Turkey<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. This increased expectations of and pressure to adopt commitments on climate action<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup> and to demonstrate leadership in it<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par13">Before 1992, climate change discussions in Mexico were limited to the Ministries of Foreign Affairs (MoFA) and Environment (MoE)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. Academics from Universidad Nacional Aut&#x000f3;noma de M&#x000e9;xico (UNAM, the acronym in Spanish) became involved in research and debates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup> and their supportive approach on climate negotiations informed and influenced Mexico&#x02019;s involvement over longer term<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. Domestic relevance of climate change increased after the entry into force of the Convention and when the negotiations on the KP started in 1995<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. At the end of the 1994&#x02013;2000 administration, Mexico ratified the KP and developed a National Strategy on Climate Change (NSCC) which, however, was not implemented<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. The withdrawal of the U.S. from the KP reduced the prospects for a carbon market in North America at the beginning of the 2000&#x02013;2006 administration, thus weakening interest in the topic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. But after the European Union (EU) ratified KP, interest in climate policy and the KP&#x02019;s Clean Development Mechanism (CDM) increased again<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. This administration also published a NSCC, but it was not implemented as this happened in the last months of its 6-year term<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par14">In the 2006&#x02013;2012 term, climate action included the early publication of a third NSCC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup> in 2007 and the first Special Program on Climate Change (SPCC)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup> in 2009, the adoption of a voluntary mitigation target, a proposal for the Green Climate Fund (GCF), the organisation of the COP 16 in Mexico and the enactment of the General Law on Climate Change (GLCC) at the end of the administration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>. Initiatives to reduce emissions from deforestation and forest degradation (REDD+) (e.g. in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>) and reforestation programs were also developed (e.g. in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>).</p><p id="Par15">In the most recent 2012&#x02013;2018 term, climate action continued under the framework of the GLCC but it had lower priority and limited funding<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. The term witnessed the update of the NSCC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup> and the SPCC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>; the creation of a carbon tax<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>; the publication of the Nationally Determined Contribution (NDC); and the development of energy projects. The national REDD+ strategy was published in August 2017 and the design and creation of a cap-and-trade system for GHGs advanced in the final months of 2018<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup>. The GLCC was reformed in May 2018<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup> to formally include the pledges of the NDC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>General assessment of climate action</title><p id="Par16">Mexico&#x02019;s climate leadership<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup> consists mostly of pledges and adoption of legislation but its actions have not yet changed its greenhouse gas emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, it is possible to characterize the performance of early actions using published and official information. Between 1994 and 2006 there were few advances yielding measurable results as the institutional frameworks were not yet in place. It is notable that the first two administrations published their NSCC at the end of their terms, indicating the issue had a low priority. The KP marked a turning point for climate action. It was signed in 1997 but only after 2005 was it possible to start its implementation. The number of CDM projects provides one proxy of climate action at this stage. A total of 192 Mexican projects are registered under the CDM and they are expected to mitigate 283.9 MtCO<sub>2</sub>e by 2030<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup>; a significant 42% of 2015 emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref></sup>. A third of the projects were registered under the VFQ&#x02019;s administration, 52% under FCH&#x02019;s and 15% under that of EPN&#x02019;s. VFQ&#x02019;s administration clearly took up the opportunities created by the KP and CDM projects thrived under FCH. EPN&#x02019;s administration underperformed with regard to CDM although Mexico signed the Doha Amendment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup> and created in 2014 a flexible carbon tax aiming at stimulating domestic demand for CDM certified emission reductions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>, which however was not implemented<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par17">The implementation of the SPCCs exemplifies action in the most recent 2006-2018 period. The 2009&#x02013;2012&#x02019;s SPCC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup> had an objective to reduce 51 MtCO<sub>2</sub>e/year and by 2012 the results exceeded its goal by 4%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup>. The 2014&#x02013;2018&#x02019;s SPCC in turn set an objective to reduce 83.2 MtCO<sub>2</sub>e/year<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup> but by 2018 only achieved 37.2% of the target<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref></sup>. Although the rate of increase of emissions diminished in 2010&#x02013;2015, the yearly increase is still of about 0.9% per year<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref></sup>. The energy sector was an important priority for EPN&#x02019;s administration, but the emission factor of the national electricity grid increased 16% from 2014 to 2018<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref></sup> evidencing the lower priority given to renewable energy and climate change in the energy sector strategy.</p><p id="Par18">Climate action can also be explored considering resources dedicated to it, particularly through the environmental sector. Budget allocated to the MoE increased under FCH&#x02019;s term: the last budget allocated in 2012<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref></sup> by his administration was 212% higher than that allocated in 2006<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref></sup> in the final year of VFQ (converted to U.S. dollars)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref></sup>. When adjusted by inflation in the same period<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref></sup> the increase was 165%. The budget of the MoE in 2018<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref></sup> at the end of EPN&#x02019;s period was only 47% of that granted in 2012<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref></sup> (37% when adjusted with inflation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref></sup>). Mexico was the world&#x02019;s second largest recipient of multilateral climate finance between 2004 and 2014 after Morocco<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref></sup> but has since fallen to the fourth place<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>A chronology of presidential attention</title><p id="Par19">A total of 968 communications published by presidential offices referred to climate change in the period of analysis (30 by EZPL, 65 by VFQ, 517 by FCH, and 356 by EPN); the list is presented in the supplementary online material (Supplementary Data&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> indicates the number of documents referring to climate change by month.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Number of publications mentioning climate change per month published in the public websites of presidential offices in Mexico.</title><p>The period spans four federal administrations&#x000a0;from December 1994 to November 2018; points represent the total number of communications published by&#x000a0;presidential offices mentioning climate change retrieved from&#x000a0;the public websites per calendar month.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_14048_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e759"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows that attention paid by Mexican presidential administrations to climate change exhibits similar patterns of ups and downs reported in previous studies from elsewhere (e.g. in refs. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref></sup>). Before 1998 there were practically no references to climate change and presidential mentions start in late 1997 to the processes around the KP. This corroborates that while climate change was discussed at the time domestically in a bottom-up way<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup> and in the context of international negotiations, it had not reached the attention of the executive. Mentions became more frequent in 2005 and specifically after 2007, reaching the maximum in late 2010 driven by the organisation of COP 16 in Cancun. From 2013 to mid 2015 attention declined, to increase again in late 2015 driven by the celebration of COP 21 in Paris and the participation of EPN in North American fora in summer 2016<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref></sup>. Attention then declined in 2018. In the next sections, we will outline the main changes in the systemic and governmental agendas during this period to help understand these changes in attention.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>International agreements and domestic legislation</title><p id="Par21">The inclusion of climate change into the systemic agenda has been gradual. The signing of the KP in 1997 and the Kyoto Protocol&#x02019;s entry into force (KPEIF) in 2005, were the first important developments in the period of analysis. They enabled the development of CDM projects and untapped international climate finance. The next milestones were the enactment of the GLCC in 2012, the adoption of the PA in 2015 and the reform of the GLCC in 2018. The organisation of COP 16 in 2010 was important for presidential attention. COPs are not only international focusing events, but a period during which the systemic agenda is created, reviewed and revised. The systemic agenda based on agreements under the UNFCCC did not translate into responsibilities, strategies and policies for practical implementation until domestic legislation was adopted. Before this happened, advances were contingent to direct executive mandates and mostly relied on external development of institutional frameworks under the UNFCCC.</p><p id="Par22">After COP 16, Mexico&#x02019;s role in the UNFCCC process was deemed so successful for restoring the negotiation process, that a few years later in 2016 Patricia Espinosa, who was Minister of the MoFA, became the Executive Secretary of the UNFCCC (e.g. in refs. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref></sup>). Actions developed in the 2006&#x02013;2012 term were innovative and ambitious, however they had no legal protection from political changes until the GLCC was enacted<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. The law included targets conditional to the adoption of an international agreement and provision of adequate international finance, to reduce emissions 30% by 2020 and 50% by 2050<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. The fact that these goals were aspirational and involved 2020 and 2050 as the key points in time for evaluation undermined accountability as there were no targets for all administrations spanning the timeframe (e.g. the 2012&#x02013;2018). The law has been crucial in keeping climate change on the governmental agenda but it lacks concrete mechanisms for implementation, particularly regarding financing, coordination of climate action and its monitoring and evaluation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. Some challenges of the implementation of the GLCC relate to its design, while others relate to difficulties in implementation processes and obstacles related to financial capacity and political will<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. Three years later, when the PA was adopted in 2015, Mexico formalized its pledges for climate action at the international level. The goals of the GLCC were updated and communicated by defining conditional and non-conditional targets for 2030<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref></sup>. These new targets defined in the NDC were incorporated into the GLCC in May 2018<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>National development plans</title><p id="Par23">Next we examine how climate change was defined in the governmental agendas. Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> below reports the number of references to climate change and how it was described and addressed in the NDPs.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Mentions and definition of climate change in Mexican NDPs (1994&#x02013;2018).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Term</th><th>Mentions</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1994&#x02013;2000, EZPL</td><td>0</td><td>Climate change is not mentioned or considered a problem. However, it refers to problems associated with causes or consequences of climate change but without mentioning it (e.g. deforestation, morbidity, urban air pollution, migration, solid waste and waste water management). Total number of words 70,494; mentions of climate change per 10,000 words: 0.00.</td></tr><tr><td>2000&#x02013;2006, FVQ</td><td>5</td><td>Climate change is mentioned as a polemical issue and the level of development in Mexico is considered to prevent the adoption of emission reduction targets. Mitigation measures would be promoted in the energy sector if they do not threaten national development. Need for adaptation and impacts of climate change are not mentioned. Total number of words 88,206; mentions of climate change per 10,000 words: 0.57.</td></tr><tr><td>2006&#x02013;2012, FCH</td><td>39</td><td>Climate change is acknowledged as an unequivocal environmental problem. It is characterized with statistics and scientific information; the NDP has specific sections for mitigation and adaptation and specific objectives, strategies and actions. Sources of emissions, sectorial actions and relevant actors are identified. There is willingness to play an active and relevant role in international negotiations and the need to increase the global scale of mitigation efforts is recognized. Total number of words 105,202; mentions of climate change per 10,000 words: 3.71.</td></tr><tr><td>2012&#x02013;2018, EPN</td><td>18</td><td>The NDP mentions climate change in the context of natural risks without elaborating on the causes or options for mitigation and adaptation. There are no specific sections or objectives for climate action. The link between economic development and carbon emissions is acknowledged but climate action is only described at the level of strategies and actions and specific objectives are not set; it is subordinated to more general objectives of green growth and transition to a low carbon economy thus not elaborating on adaptation. Previous leadership at international level is acknowledged. The country will maintain a role of a committed participant in international processes to defend national interests. Total number of words 68,728; mentions of climate change per 10,000 words: 2.62.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par24">Climate change was not even mentioned in the NDP between 1994 and 2000. However, the plan mentioned concerns and actions that relate to aspects of climate mitigation and adaptation. Thus some actions and policies moved forward, but without a strategic approach. This could be expected given that concrete institutional frameworks for climate action had not yet been developed, domestically or globally. The situation did not change much in the next administration which described climate change as a polemical issue whilst leaving the window open for no-regret opportunities. This explains partly how the KPEIF reinvigorated domestic interest in the issue<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. The initial reluctance to reduce emissions is consistent with the non-Annex I concern at the time that climate action might adversely affects economic development, oil production<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>, and in the case of Mexico, public budget.</p><p id="Par25">Climate change was significantly redefined in the 2007&#x02013;2012&#x02019;s NDP. It included the highest number of references to the issue and presented a comprehensive description of the problem, implications and possible solutions and their translation into proactive implementation. Reference to the need for greater global mitigation ambition in the plan suggests why Mexico adopted a voluntary goal in 2008. The aspiration for a proactive international role also offers insight into the origins of the Mexican climate fund proposal and interest to organize COP 16.</p><p id="Par26">The governmental change in 2012 brought another redefinition of climate change as a public problem. It was now mentioned in the context of natural disasters and international negotiations but not discussed in terms of its causes; specific mitigation and adaptation objectives were not defined. Climate change was deemphasized and subordinated to strategies promoting green growth and low carbon development. However, the institutional framework already in place (i.e. GLCC) helped to keep climate change in the executive agenda and other areas of the government.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Agenda changes and changes in attention levels</title><p id="Par27">We plot the cumulative number of monthly mentions of climate change in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> to examine the change in the trend and not the discrete monthly variations (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The smoother pattern enables the identification of periods with more or less stable attention levels (i.e. the period from 1998 to 2005 is particularly stable). Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> also shows the dates of changes of administrations and the months when the main developments in the systemic agenda occured.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Evolution of attention to climate change by Mexican presidents from 1994 to 2018 as depicted by the trends in the cumulative number of communications.</title><p>Governmental changes and the dates of key developments in international and domestic frameworks are identified. <bold>a</bold> Presents the cumulative monthly communications and key events modifying the systemic and governmental agendas; the lower <bold>b</bold> Presents the Chow test statistic to test the structural differences in attention levels.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_14048_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e943"/></fig></p><p id="Par28">The level of attention in terms of the slope changes around the dates of the relevant international events and around 2006/2007 and 2012/2013. The lower panel in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> presents the Chow test statistics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref></sup> obtained when analyzing the structural changes for the segments of interest. Results show that for each of the four presidencies, the Chow test statistic peaks around the dates of the selected international events. This confirms that these events produced important structural changes in presidential attention to climate change. However, this is not the case for the enactment and reform of the GLCC. These events did not produced a structural change in presidential attention. The impact of the GLCC enactment in June 2012 and its reform in May 2018 on presidential attention is challenging to assess. These events occurred only a few months before the end of the pertinent administrations leaving a short time for a reaction. Also, it is not possible to know what the level of attention of the following presidencies would have been had the legislation not been enacted. Finally, it can be seen that the attention patterns in the last months of the leaving administrations and the first months of entering ones in 2006 and 2012 are structurally different and data cannot be pooled together as the Chow test statistic presents prononunced peaks. The governmental change in December 2000 is more subtle indicating similar attention patterns before and after this date.</p><p id="Par29">We identify nine segments with different slopes (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) which also maximized the coefficients of determination (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>). In all cases the regressions are significant at 0.01; after the signing of the KP in all cases the <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> are higher than 90%.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Regression analysis in the level of attention of Mexican presidents to climate change after changes in governmental and systemic agendas (1994&#x02013;2018).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Identification-Code</th><th>EZPL-1</th><th>EZPL-2</th><th>VFQ-1</th><th>VFQ-2</th><th>FCH-1</th><th>FCH-2</th><th>EPN-1</th><th>EPN-2</th><th>EPN-3</th></tr><tr><th>Segment for Regression</th><th>A</th><th>B</th><th>C</th><th>D</th><th>E</th><th>F</th><th>G</th><th>H</th><th>I</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Start date</td><td>Dec-94</td><td>Jan-98</td><td>Dec-00</td><td>Mar-05</td><td>Dec-06</td><td>Dec-10</td><td>Dec-12</td><td>Sep-15</td><td>Nov-17</td></tr><tr><td>End date</td><td>Dec-97</td><td>Nov-00</td><td>Feb-05</td><td>Nov-06</td><td>Nov-10</td><td>Nov-12</td><td>Aug-15</td><td>Oct-17</td><td>Nov-18</td></tr><tr><td><italic>n</italic> (months)</td><td>37</td><td>35</td><td>51</td><td>21</td><td>48</td><td>24</td><td>33</td><td>26</td><td>13</td></tr><tr><td>Level of attention <italic>b</italic> (slope, comms/month)</td><td>0.101</td><td>0.625</td><td>0.611</td><td>1.634</td><td>5.878</td><td>7.003</td><td>2.552</td><td>7.772</td><td>3.698</td></tr><tr><td>Coefficient of Determination (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>)</td><td>51.3%</td><td>90.6%</td><td>93.4%</td><td>97.0%</td><td>98.9%</td><td>98.7%</td><td>98.4%</td><td>97.2%</td><td>97.8%</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Comparison between segments</th><th>A and B</th><th>B and C</th><th>C and D</th><th>D and E</th><th>E and F</th><th>F and G</th><th>G and H</th><th>H and I</th><th>G and I</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Change in Level of Attention, <italic>b</italic> (%)<sup>a</sup></td><td>517%</td><td>&#x02212;2.2%</td><td>167.5%</td><td>259.8%</td><td>19.1%</td><td>&#x02212;63.6%</td><td>204.5%</td><td>&#x02212;52.4%</td><td>44.9%</td></tr><tr><td><italic>t</italic> value (absolute values)</td><td>13.52</td><td>0.33</td><td>14.63</td><td>38.08</td><td>5.75</td><td>24.30</td><td>18.87</td><td>12.80</td><td>6.45</td></tr><tr><td>Sig-Dif. Between Segments (<italic>t</italic>-test <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.01)</td><td>Yes</td><td>No</td><td>Yes</td><td>Yes</td><td>Yes</td><td>Yes</td><td>Yes</td><td>Yes</td><td>Yes</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Estimated as <italic>b</italic><sub>2</sub>/<italic>b</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;1</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par30">Presidential attention to climate change increased following changes in the international climate negotiations; this is reactive behavior. The dates when decisions were made at international events became inflection points. These increases were substantial for EZPL, VFQ, and EPN as attention increased by 517%, 167%, and 204%, respectively. In the case of FCH, the effect of COP 16 is smaller (i.e. 19%); the most visible effect is an upwards displacement of cumulative values in December 2010.</p><p id="Par31">The level of attention at the beginning of EPN&#x02019;s administration until August 2015 was lower than that of the previous government. During this period the focus of the executive was on structural reforms (e.g. energy, education, fiscal matters). The post-COP 21 period can be divided into two segments (H and I). Attention levels increased a couple of months before COP 21, to reach similar levels as those observed during in 2006&#x02013;2012. During the last phase of this presidency (Segment I), the level of attention declined and as results of the evaluation of the SPCC 2014&#x02013;2018 indicate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref></sup> attention did not translate into effective implementation.</p><p id="Par32">Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows that following the 2000 elections there was no significant change in the slope despite the partisan change. Climate change was still not a priority and it was not yet defined as a salient public issue in the corresponding NDPs. In contrast, although the change in administration in 2006 did not involved a partisan change, the redefinition of climate change and its inclusion into the NDP indicates a significant difference in the attention level of this administration. These observations resonate with the punctuated equilibrium model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Attention in the planning and implementation of the agenda</title><p id="Par33">The governmental agenda is formally defined in the NDPs. To assess the level of attention to climate change during the planning of the governmental agenda in contrast to its implementation, we consider the communications retrieved from the presidential websites. To characterize the level of attention we plot the number of documents retrieved against the number and mentions in the NDP for each administration.</p><p id="Par34">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> shows a consistent relationship between attention levels to climate change in the NDP during the planning of the governmental agendas and in the number of communications retrieved from the presidential websites during its implementation period. The coefficient of determination (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>) is 94% for a linear regression. This parameter is a good predictor of the level of attention observed during the past governmental periods. It is necessary to continue monitoring the public agenda and attention paid to different issues to generate a record for better understanding the processes associated with the planning and implementation of climate policy.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Relationship between the number of mentions in NDPs and the number of communications&#x000a0;made by presidential offices referring to climate change for each presidency of Mexico (1994&#x02013;2018). Data points indicate the total number&#x000a0;of mentions and attention levels paid to climate change&#x000a0;in the planning and the implementation of the governmental agendas in the corresponding 6-year periods;&#x000a0;regression confidence interval for 95% level.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_14048_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1422"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Inclusion of climate change into the governmental agendas</title><p id="Par35">Our results provide previously lacking evidence on how the NDPs critically construe the governmental agenda and are a good indicator of the expected attention levels in each governmental term. It is therefore worth looking at past changes in governmental agendas to explore how policy windows emerged and how Kingdon&#x02019;s three streams confluenced at the time.</p><p id="Par36">FCH&#x02019;s term and NDP were a key for the inclusion of climate action into the Mexican policy agenda. Before running for presidency he was director of the public investment bank BANOBRAS and as Minister of Energy he was involved in renewable energy projects and procurement of international climate finance. Nevertheless, during the electoral campaign of 2006 climate change was not yet an issue and it was not part of his political platform<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. In the two televised debates before the elections, he did not mention climate change and only once referred to the financial opportunities under KP when echoing a proposal of one of his opponents, Patricia Mercado<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref></sup>. Still, he made proposals and took positions that helped creating political conditions for the inclusion of the issue in the agenda. He promised in his discourses a responsible government with a proactive role in international negotiations and one open to the advice of scientists such as the Nobel Prize recipient Dr. Mario Molina who by that time had proposed a change in petrol formula sold in the country to improve air quality<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref></sup>. Climate change thus became included into the governmental agenda after these debates, between June 2006 and before the publication of FCH&#x02019;s NDP in May 2007.</p><p id="Par37">In 2006, Mexican newspapers gave limited attention to climate change and considered it a secondary issue<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. This was also the case with newspapers in Spain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref></sup>. Thus in the spanish-speaking world climate change was not in the public agenda. However, in newspapers published in english, attention to climate change increased substantially from September to November 2006 as a result of the publication of the Stern Review: The Economics of Climate Change<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref></sup> and the release of Al Gore&#x02019;s documentary An Inconvenient Truth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref></sup>. These events helped construe climate change as an important problem with plausible solutions for the receptive FCH&#x02019;s team preparing the NDP.</p><p id="Par38">For the last administration considered,&#x000a0;in the NDP and the first 2 years of EPN&#x02019;s mandate less attention was given to climate change. It is impossible to identify all reasons behind a policy change<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> but some can be hypothesized. The 2012 elections returned to power the new PRI (e.g. in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref></sup>) and during the previous 12 years climate advocates might have not interacted with other political groups than PAN. Therefore, the agenda of the new government was framed around other issues: new administrations advance their own pet issues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. At this time, climate change was not an urgent problem. The country had already passed the GLCC in 2012, when solutions are already in place, incentives for attention are reduced as it can be perceived that the problem is solved<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. The 2012/2013 policy window also coincided with a period of the lowest level of global public attention to climate change after 2007<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref></sup>; the attention only increased later in the runup to COP 21 in 2015. Nevertheless, the high sensitivity of EPN to public opinion at international level made him politically receptive to the issue and lead to higher reactive attention around COP 21. However, it faded away without becoming translated into mitigation efforts or higher budgetary priorities. Falling oil prices also reduced public revenue and climate action and the environmental agenda as a whole faced budget cuts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par39">Mexico had a general election in July 2018 and Andr&#x000e9;s Manuel L&#x000f3;pez Obrador (AMLO) was elected after running for the presidency for the third time. This produced another partisan change to the leftist Movement for National Regeneration (MORENA). Two important changes followed. The new administration marks the end of centre-right neoliberal policies (e.g. in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>) and the president obtained partisan majority in the federal Congress for the first time since 1997 (e.g. in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>). A question remains whether presidential attention paid to climate change under these new circumstances will follow similar patterns as in the last four administrations (e.g. in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Climate change was not an important issue in AMLO&#x02019;s 2006 and 2012 campaigns<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref></sup>. However, in the 2018 campaign his climate change platform was assessed by a group of environmental NGOs the best among the candidates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref></sup>. Still, his campaign focused on poverty alleviation, vulnerable groups such as rural and indigenous communities, austerity and a fight against corruption. It is unclear how AMLO will advance the climate strategy proposed in the campaign. However, reframing the need for mitigation and adaptation actions around topics as the need to protect vulnerable groups in the context of poverty alleviation, or as means to reduce budget pressures via savings can help keeping the topic in the agenda (e.g. in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>).</p><p id="Par40">Since the end of 2018, global public interest on climate change has increased again, including in Europe and the U.S.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref></sup>. This has been fuelled by the awarding of the Nobel Prize in Economics to William Nordhaus for his studies on the global economy and the climate, and the climate campaigns of swedish teenager Greta Thunberg and other social movements. If the momentum continues to build up and if the priority of climate change increases among the public, the governmental attention to the issue in Mexico might increase. Other foreseeable events that can alter presidential attention before 2024 in Mexico are the U.S. presidential elections in 2020 and the first revision of the implementation of the PA in 2023<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par41">We analyzed the NDPs and public information from 1994 to 2018 to characterize the evolution of presidential attention to climate change in Mexico. Our results are consistent with agenda-setting literature, particularly with Kingdon&#x02019;s<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> multiple streams model and the punctuated equilibrium model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> but also provide new empirical evidence that has been lacking to date. The consideration of the changes in the different agendas facilitates the understanding of the key observable developments of climate policy and action in Mexico in the last 24 years. We contribute to the existing body of knowledge by identifying the differential impacts of changes in the systemic and governmental agendas to leaders&#x02019; attention to climate change. Our results indicate that changes in the systemic agenda driven by international agreements under the UNFCCC resulted in reactive changes which are substantial but potentially reversible. In contrast, the comprehensive inclusion of climate change and responses to it into the governmental agenda lead to higher, more proactive and more stable attention levels. We can conclude that while international agreements and domestic legislation establish the minimum baseline for including climate change into governmental action<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>, proactive and ambitious action is underpinned by executive governmental plans.</p><p id="Par42">A question remains whether governmental agendas of other countries evolve in a comparable manner than Mexico&#x02019;s. This is an important area for future research given the prevalence of development planning globally (e.g. in refs. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>). It is also important to explore whether similar processes involving systemic and governmental agendas are at play at sub-national levels (e.g. State/Regional and Municipal/Local Level Development Plans) and among different implementing ministries and institutions (e.g. Ministry of Environment, Ministry of Energy, etc) to help further improving our understanding of the factors behind diffusion and mainstreaming of climate action.</p><p id="Par43">As our results demonstrate, it is critical not only to keep track of the enactment of climate legislation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref></sup> and goals stated in the NDCs, but also to assess and promote the inclusion of climate action into governmental plans since they define the priorities and resources for practical implementation of such legislation and contributions. While we have focused here on levels of attention, it is important not to forget that, to fully evaluate policy implementation, the efficacy of climate actions needs to be assessed in terms of changes in emissions and levels of vulnerability, too.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>General approach</title><p id="Par44">We first performed a review of the literature on the main developments related to the design and implementation of climate action and associated policies in Mexico in the period of interest. This enabled us to identify the observable outcomes of implementation processes. It is within the context provided by these developments that we analyze whether attention levels match the actions implemented and if changes in the agendas of interest explain changes in attention levels and climate policy.</p><p id="Par45">We performed a longitudinal study of attention paid by Mexican presidents to climate change from 1994 to 2018 using content analysis, a systematic approach to translate qualitative information into quantitative data using defined frameworks to analyze it, explore statistical relationships and to make inferences<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. The method has been used to examine a range of issues including the attention given to climate change in newspapers in Canada<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, Mexico<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>, and the U.S.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref></sup>, and in scientists&#x02019; congressional testimonies on climate change in the US<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref></sup>. Coding of the content of information sources over time has been used to examine policy change in light of the punctuated equilibrium model, too<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. In what follows, we explain how the material was retrieved, coded and analysed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Presidential attention on climate change</title><p id="Par46">The Mexican federal government publishes different types of information on public websites as part of its communication and transparency policies, including transcripts of speeches, press releases, interviews, informative notes, and other official communications. The archieved websites of past Mexican presidencies remain online in the active presidential page<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref></sup>. We searched the four presidential websites for publications where the terms climate change, global warming or greenhouse effect occurred (e.g. in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref></sup>). All documents found published by the presidential offices&#x000a0;were retrieved and given an individual code number. A database was built including the title and date of publication. Our analysis focuses on these documents and not on strategic documents such as the National Communications submitted by the Mexican Government to the UNFCCC, or texts of specific legislation or laws since these documents are prepared by technical experts, by staff of technical bodies of the MoE or the Federal Congress, and not by the presidential offices. By focusing on the information published by the presidential office our objective is to generate a proxy of how level of attention to climate change in the closest circle of the execuctive has evolved over time.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>The systemic and govermental agendas</title><p id="Par47">One of our objectives is to understand how the inclusion of climate change in the systemic&#x000a0;and governmental agendas relates to presidential attention to climate change. In order to understand this, we describe when the main advances originating from the international agreements and domestic climate legislation occured and how they contributed to the definition of the systemic climate agenda in the country.</p><p id="Par48">The governmental agenda is inscribed to the NDP which is published by each Mexican federal administration in the first months after coming into power in the country&#x02019;s Official Gazzette, Diario Oficial de la Federaci&#x000f3;n in Spanish (DOF). NDPs are prepared according to the Planning Law<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. We accessed the DOF to obtain the NDPs of the four federal administrations from 1994 to 2018<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. These were published on the 31 May 1995 by the administration of EZPL, 30 May 2001 by the administration of VFQ, 31 May 2007 by the government of FCH and 20 May 2013 by the administration of EPN. The four NDPs are substantial documents: their word counts vary between 67,000 and 105,000 words. To determine whether climate change is included in each governmental agenda we first made a search for the presence and frequency of mentions of climate change, global warming and greenhouse effect in the NDPs following the standard practice (e.g. in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref></sup>), to obtain the total count of mentions of climate change. We then examined how climate change as a problem and potential solutions were framed. We could thus establish whether climate change was included in the governmental agenda of the four presidencies and whether it had been reframed or redefined in the NDPs in line with the punctuated equilibrium model. The dates of the governmental changes define temporal boundaries to verify if changes in the definition of the problem in the NDPs was associated to changes in attention levels during the presidential period.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Analyses made</title><p id="Par49">We first built a chronology of presidential attention to climate change considering the number of publications mentioning climate change per month as a metric of attention. Our hypotheses are that changes stemming from the systemic agenda might modify the presidential attention trends reactively, while changes in the governmental agenda might indicate a more proactive attention towards climate change. Considering that the executive has more control over the governmental agenda when climate change is explicitly included in the NDP in the planning stage, we hypothesize that it will also get more attention during the implementation phase; how a problem is defined provides information on how it will be dealt with<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">111</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par50">The dates of changes in administrations and of the key events shaping the systemic agenda are used to assess differences in the levels of attention and their patterns; the changes in administration represent the changes in the governmental agenda reflected in the corresponding NDPs. Based on the segmentation drawn from the consideration of these dates, we use the cumulative number of communications to identify periods with stable levels of attention and estimate the slopes and statistical differences of each of these periods through an ordinary least squares regression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref></sup>. The Chow test statistic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref></sup> is used to identify structural breaks in attention patterns in the different periods identified; this is to confirm the dates around which data can be segmented and improve the resulting linear regressions. The Chow test statistic is obtained by comparing the information of three linear regressions: two presumably different groups of data and the pooled information of both groups.</p><p id="Par51">For each administration, we estimated the linear regression of the cumulative communications over the whole period of 72 months and made 66 iterations and estimated the Chow test statistic for 66 possible divisions of the data in two segements between the 5th and 70th months; the maximum values of the Chow test statistic indicates the months at which the time series can be divided to analyze the data as different segments&#x000a0;producing better results. The same approach is followed to assess structural breaks around the dates when governmental changes took place and when the GLCC was enacted and reformed. By comparing the differences in the slopes of the linear regressions we can test whether changes stemming from the governmental or systemic agendas alter the level of attention.</p><p id="Par52">Finally, we compare the frequency of mentions of climate change in the NDPs with the number of documents retrieved from each presidential website to assess the similarity in attention levels between the governmental agenda at the planning phase at the start of each term and during each 6-year period when this is implemented. We test how well the data on attention levels at the planning and implementation phases fits to a linear regression using the number of mentions in NDPs as an independent variable; we compute the confidence interval for the regression at 95% level using a <italic>t</italic>-distribution.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec17"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41467_2019_14048_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Description of Additional Supplementary Files</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41467_2019_14048_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Data 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Peer review information</bold>
<italic>Nature Communications</italic> thanks the anonymous reviewer(s) for their contribution to the peer review of this work.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> is available for this paper at 10.1038/s41467-019-14048-7.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank SGL, KCG, MVC, MYRG, DOP, LHR of Environmental Engineering and Professional Application Projects at ITESO for their support to the project; and to two colleagues for their comments to earlier versions of the manuscript. ABT was supported by funding from the European Union&#x02019;s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme under the Marie Sk&#x00142;odowska-Curie grant agreement No. 707539. JP was supported by funding from the Economic and Social Research Council (ESRC) to the Centre for Climate Change Economics and Policy (CCCEP) (ESRC grant number ES/K006576/1).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>A.B.T. conceived the idea; analysis was conducted by A.B.T. and P.L.V. A.B.T. led the writing, J.P. and P.L.V. contributed to the writing.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated or analysed during this study are included in this published article (and its supplementary information files). The Supplementary Data&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">1</xref> presents the database of the communications retreived from the presidential websites.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par53">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pralle</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Agenda-setting and climate change</article-title><source>Environ. Politics</source><year>2009</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09644010903157115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kingdon, J. <italic>Agendas, alternatives, and public policies</italic> 2nd edn. (Longman, New York, 1995).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Elder</surname><given-names>Ch</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Agenda building and the politics of aging</article-title><source>Policy Sci. J.</source><year>1984</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0047279400022972</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What drives media attention for climate change? Explaining issue attention in Australian, German and Indian print media from 1996 to 2010</article-title><source>Int. Commun. Gaz.</source><year>2014</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1748048513504169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hilgartner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosk</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The rise and fall of social problems: a public arenas model</article-title><source>Am. J. Sociol.</source><year>1988</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/228951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Baumgartner, F. R. &#x00026; Jones, B. D. <italic>Agendas and instability in American politics</italic> 2nd edn. (University of Chicago Press, U.S, 2009).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dearing, J. W. &#x00026; Rogers, E. M. <italic>Agenda Setting</italic>. (Sage, Thousand Oaks, 1996).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sampei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoyagi-Usui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mass-media coverage, its influence on public awareness of climate-change issues, and implications for Japan&#x02019;s national campaign to reduce greenhouse gas emissions</article-title><source>Glob. Environ. Change</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2008.10.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Downs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Up and down with ecology: the &#x02018;issue-attention&#x02019; cycle</article-title><source>Public Interest</source><year>1972</year><volume>28</volume><issue>summer</issue><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Baumgartner, F. &#x00026; Jones, B. D. <italic>Agendas and instability in American politics</italic>. (University of Chicago, Chicago, 1993).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Deines</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Havice</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global warming coverage in the media: trends in a Mexico City newspaper</article-title><source>Sci. Commun.</source><year>2010</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1075547009340336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Meisner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental discourses and discourse coalitions in the reconfiguration of Peru's environmental governance</article-title><source>Environ. Commun.: A J. Nat. Cult.</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17524032.2012.700522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kingdon</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A model of agenda-setting, with applications</article-title><source>Law Rev.</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>337</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindquist</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vedlitz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Explaining media and congressional atttention to global climate change, 1969-2005: an empirical test of agenda-setting theory</article-title><source>Political Res. Q.</source><year>2011</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1065912909346744</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jakob</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Will history repeat itself? Economic convergence and convergence in energy use patterns</article-title><source>Energy Econ.</source><year>2012</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eneco.2011.07.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gupta, J. <italic>The climate change convention and developing countries: from conflict to consensus</italic>? (Kluwer Academic Publishers, Netherlands, 1997).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UNFCCC. <italic>Nationally Determined Contributions. United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change</italic>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://unfccc.int/process-and-meetings/the-paris-agreement/nationally-determined-contributions-ndcs">https://unfccc.int/process-and-meetings/the-paris-agreement/nationally-determined-contributions-ndcs</ext-link> (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nachmany, M. and Setzer, J. <italic>Global trends in climate change legislation and litigation: 2018 a snapshot. Policy Brief</italic>. (Centre for Climate Change Economics and Policy, Grantham Research Institute on Climate Change and the Environment, U.K., 2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahchong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodds</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anthropogenic climate change coverage in two Canadian newspapers, the Toronto Star and the Globe and Mail, from 1988 to 2007</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Policy</source><year>2012</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envsci.2011.09.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A history of international climate change policy</article-title><source>WIREs Clim. Change</source><year>2010</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>636</fpage><lpage>653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wcc.67</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Resosudarmo, B. P., Ardiansyah, F. and Napitupulu, L. The Dynamics of Climate Change Governance in Indonesia, in <italic>Climate Governance in the Developing World</italic> (eds Held, D., Roger, Ch. &#x00026; Nag, E. M.) Ch. 4 (Polity, Cambridge, 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fletcher, R. Making &#x000b4;Peace with Nature`: Costa Rica&#x000b4;s Campaign for Climate Neutrality. in <italic>Climate Governance in the Developing World</italic> (eds Held, D., Roger, Ch. &#x00026; Nag, E. M.) Ch. 8 (Polity, Cambridge, 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Held, D., Roger, Ch. and Nag, E. M. A Green Revolution: China&#x000b4;s Governance of Energy and Climate Change, in <italic>Climate Governance in the Developing World</italic> (eds Held, D., Roger, Ch. and Nag, E. M.) Ch. 2 (Polity, Cambridge, 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Masters, L. Reaching the Crossroads: The Development of Climate Governance in South Africa. in <italic>Climate Governance in the Developing World</italic> (eds Held, D., Roger, Ch. and Nag, E. M.) Ch. 13 (Polity, Cambridge, 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lee, J. S. Low Carbon Green Growth and Climate Change Governance in South Korea. in <italic>Climate Governance in the Developing World</italic> (eds Held, D., Roger, Ch. &#x00026; Nag, E. M.) Ch. 5 (Polity, Cambridge, 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change governance: history, future, and triple-loop learning?</article-title><source>WIREs Clim. Change</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wcc.388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Meilstrup, P. The Runaway Summit: The Background Story of the Danish Presidency of COP 15, the UN Climate Change Conference, in <italic>Danish Foreign Policy Yearbook</italic> (eds Hvdit, N. &#x00026; Mouritzen, H.) 113&#x02013;135 (Danish Institute for International Studies, 2010).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UNFCCC. <italic>Paris Agreement</italic> (United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change, New York, 2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raftery</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Less than 2&#x02009;&#x000b0;C warming by 2011 unlikely</article-title><source>Nat. Clim. Change</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>637</fpage><lpage>641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nclimate3352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nieto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpintero</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Miguel</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Less than 2&#x02009;&#x000b0;C? An economic-environmental evaluation of the Paris Agreement</article-title><source>Ecol. Econ.</source><year>2018</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolecon.2017.10.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Held, D., Roger, C. and Nag, E. M. <italic>Editors&#x000b4; Introduction: Climate Governance in the Developing World</italic> Ch. 1 (Polity, Cambridge, 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Urrutia, A. and Villanueva, D. <italic>Abolidos, el modelo neoliberal y su pol&#x000ed;tica de pillaje, asegura AMLO</italic>. (Peri&#x000f3;dico La Jornada, Mexico, 2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Robles de la Rosa, L. <italic>Mayor&#x000ed;a absoluta vuelve al Congreso de la Uni&#x000f3;n</italic>. (Peri&#x000f3;dico Exc&#x000e9;lsior, Mexico, 2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elder</surname><given-names>Ch</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Agenda-building and the politics of aging</article-title><source>Policy Sci. J.</source><year>1984</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>129</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aguilar Villanueva, L. F. <italic>Problemas P&#x000fa;blicos y Agenda de Gobierno</italic> (MA Porr&#x000fa;a, M&#x000e9;xico, 2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Riffe, D., Lacy, S. &#x00026; Fico, F. G. <italic>Analysing Media Messages. Using Quantitative Content Analysis in Research</italic> 2nd edn (Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Publishers, Mahwah, London, 2005).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NDP. Plan Nacional de Desarrollo 1995-2000, Diario Oficial, 31 de Mayo de 1995 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.diputados.gob.mx/LeyesBiblio/compila/pnd/PND_1995-2000_31may95.doc">http://www.diputados.gob.mx/LeyesBiblio/compila/pnd/PND_1995-2000_31may95.doc</ext-link> (1995) Accessed 2nd May 2017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NDP. Plan Nacional de Desarrollo 2001-2006, Diario Oficial, 31 de Mayo de 2001 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.diputados.gob.mx/LeyesBiblio/compila/pnd/PND_2001-2006_30may01.doc">http://www.diputados.gob.mx/LeyesBiblio/compila/pnd/PND_2001-2006_30may01.doc</ext-link> (2001) Accessed 2nd May 2017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NDP. Plan Nacional de Desarrollo 2007-2012, Diario Oficial, 31 de Mayo de 2007 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.diputados.gob.mx/LeyesBiblio/compila/pnd/PND_2007-2012_31may07.doc">http://www.diputados.gob.mx/LeyesBiblio/compila/pnd/PND_2007-2012_31may07.doc</ext-link> (2007) Accessed 2nd May 2017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NDP. Plan Nacional de Desarrollo 2013-2018, Diario Oficial, 31 de Mayo de 2013 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.diputados.gob.mx/LeyesBiblio/compila/pnd/PND_2013-2018_20may13.doc">http://www.diputados.gob.mx/LeyesBiblio/compila/pnd/PND_2013-2018_20may13.doc</ext-link> (2013) Accessed 2nd May 2017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perezcano-D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Los tratados internacionales en el orden jur&#x000ed;dico Mexicano</article-title><source>Anuario Mexicano de. Derecho Internacional</source><year>2007</year><volume>VII</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>279</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Becerra Ram&#x000ed;rez, M. et al. Tratados internacionales. Se ubican jer&#x000e1;rquicamente por encima de. la leyes y. en. un. segundo plano respecto de. la Constituci&#x000f3;n Federal (Amparo En Revisi&#x000f3;n 1475/98). Cuestiones Constitucionales Rev. Mexicana de. Derecho Constitucional <bold>3</bold>, 169&#x02013;208 (2000).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">D. O. F. Ley de Planeaci&#x000f3;n, Nueva Ley Publicada en el Diario Oficial de la Federaci&#x000f3;n, 5 de Enero de 1983, Reforma DOF 16-02-2018, Diario Oficial de la Federaci&#x000f3;n (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sagasti</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>National development planning in turbulent times: new approaches and criteria for institutional design</article-title><source>World Dev.</source><year>1988</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0305-750X(88)90195-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mejia Guinad, L. B. <italic>The Changing Role of the Central Planning Offices in Latin America</italic> Vol 16, 477&#x02013;491 (Public Organization Review, 2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Waterston, A. Development planning: lessons of experience (English) http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/299401468767072805/Development-planning-lessons-of-experience (The World Bank, Washington, D.C, 1969).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>South.</collab></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c;Third World Development Plans: Strategies for a decade&#x0201d;</article-title><source>South Mag.</source><year>1986</year><volume>No. 63</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>68</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>van Anrooy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brugere</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>When fisheries influence national policy-making: an analysis of the national development strategies of major fish-producing nations in the developing world</article-title><source>Mar. Policy</source><year>2005</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.marpol.2004.05.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pulver</surname><given-names>Simone</given-names></name><name><surname>Sainz-Santamar&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>Jaime</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterizing the climate issue context in Mexico: reporting on climate change in Mexican newspapers, 1996&#x02013;2009</article-title><source>Climate and Development</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>538</fpage><lpage>551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17565529.2017.1318737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UCS. Each&#x000b4;s country share of CO2 Emissions. Union of Concerned Scientists, Available online: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ucsusa.org/global-warming/science-and-impacts/science/each-countrys-share-of-co2.html#.XEtm8M9KjOQ">https://www.ucsusa.org/global-warming/science-and-impacts/science/each-countrys-share-of-co2.html#.XEtm8M9KjOQ</ext-link> (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Adam, D. M&#x000e9;xico leads the way with carbon reduction pledge. The Guardian, disponible en linea: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.theguardian.com/environment/2008/dec/11/poznan-climate-change-mexico-carbon-pledge">http://www.theguardian.com/environment/2008/dec/11/poznan-climate-change-mexico-carbon-pledge</ext-link> (2008).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vance</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>M&#x000e9;xico passes climate-change law</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature.2012.10496</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23320285?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23320285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">D. O. F. Decreto por el que se expide la Ley General de Cambio Clim&#x000e1;tico, SEMARNAT, Diario Oficial de la Federaci&#x000f3;n, 6 June 2012, M&#x000e9;xico, D.F. (2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>El ingreso de M&#x000e9;xico a la OCDE</article-title><source>Rev. de. Comer. Exter.</source><year>1994</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>523</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">AP. Mexico formally invited to join OECD as 25th Member. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://apnews.com/5c32c538b21ed50047612bcd16725a5c">https://apnews.com/5c32c538b21ed50047612bcd16725a5c</ext-link> (Associated Press, 1994).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Geo-M&#x000e9;xico. Why Mexico is in the OECD? Geo-Mexico, The Geography of Mexico. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://geo-mexico.com/?p=8410">http://geo-mexico.com/?p=8410</ext-link> (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Selin, H. &#x00026; VanDeveer, S. D. <italic>Chaning Climates in North American Politics. Institutions Policymaking and Multilevel Governance</italic>. (MIT Press, London, 2009).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pulver, S. Climate politics in Mexico in a North American Perspective. Presented at Climate Change Politics in North America. (Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, Washington, D.C., 2006).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pulver, S. &#x0201c;A. Climate Leader? The politics and practice of climate governance in Mexico&#x0201d; in <italic>Climate Governance in the Developing World</italic> (eds D. Held, et al.) 25&#x02013;46 (MIT Press, Cambridge, 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CICC. Estrategia Nacional de Cambio Clim&#x000e1;tico M&#x000e9;xico. Comisi&#x000f3;n Intersecretarial de Cambio Clim&#x000e1;tico, Mayo 2007, M&#x000e9;xico, D.F. (2007).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">DOF. PROGRAMA Especial de Cambio Clim&#x000e1;tico 2009-2012. SEMARNAT, Diario Oficial de la Federaci&#x000f3;n, 28 de Agosto de 2009, M&#x000e9;xico (2009).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UNFCCC. Report of the conference of the parties on its sixteenth session, held in Cancun from 29 November to 10 December 2010, (United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change, Bonn, 2011) 15 March 2011.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CONAFOR. Visi&#x000f3;n de M&#x000e9;xico sobre REDD+: Hacia una estrategia nacional.Comisi&#x000f3;n Nacional Forestal, Mexico (2010).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">DOF. Reglas de Operaci&#x000f3;n del Programa ProArbol 2012. SEMARNAT, Diario Oficial de la Federaci&#x000f3;n, 21 de Diciembre de 2012, M&#x000e9;xico (2011).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Averchenkova, A. &#x00026; Guzm&#x000e1;n-Luna, S. <italic>Mexico&#x000b4;s General Law on Climate Change: Key achievements and challenges ahead</italic>. (Grantham Research Institute on Climate Change and the Environment and the Centre for Climate Change Economics and Policy, London School of Economics and Political Science, London, 2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">SEMARNAT. Estrategia Nacional de Cambio Clim&#x000e1;tico Visi&#x000f3;n 10-20-40, Primera Edici&#x000f3;n, SEMARNAT, M&#x000e9;xico (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CICC. Programa Especial de Cambio Clim&#x000e1;tico (2014-2018). Secretar&#x000ed;a de Medio Ambiente y Recursos Naturales. Available online: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.semarnat.gob.mx/sites/default/files/documentos/transparencia/programa_especial_de_cambio_climatico_2014-2018.pdf">http://www.semarnat.gob.mx/sites/default/files/documentos/transparencia/programa_especial_de_cambio_climatico_2014-2018.pdf</ext-link> (2014) Accessed 20 March 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">DOF. DECRETO por el que se reforman, adicionan y derogan diversas disposiciones de la Ley del Impuesto al Valor Agregado; de la Ley del Impuesto Especial sobre Producci&#x000f3;n y Servicios; de la Ley Federal de Derechos, se expide la Ley del Impuesto sobre la Renta, y se abrogan la Ley del Impuesto Empresarial a Tasa &#x000da;nica, y la Ley del Impuesto a los Dep&#x000f3;sitos en Efectivo (Contin&#x000fa;a en la Tercera Secci&#x000f3;n). Diario Oficial de la Federaci&#x000f3;n. 11 de Diciembre de 2013. M&#x000e9;xico, D.F.(2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CONAFOR. Estrategia Nacional para REDD+ 2017-2030. ENAREDD+. Comisi&#x000f3;n Nacional Forestal, Agosto de 2017, M&#x000e9;xico (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">SEMARNAT. Programa de pruebas del Sistema de comercio de Emisiones. Secretaria de Medio Ambiente y Recursos Naturales, 27 de Noviembre de 2018. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gob.mx/semarnat/acciones-y-programas/programa-de-prueba-del-sistema-de-comercio-de-emisiones-179414">https://www.gob.mx/semarnat/acciones-y-programas/programa-de-prueba-del-sistema-de-comercio-de-emisiones-179414</ext-link> (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">DOF. DECRETO por el que se reforman y adicionan diversas disposiciones a la Ley General de Cambio Clim&#x000e1;tico. SEMARNAT Diario Oficial de la Federaci&#x000f3;n, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dof.gob.mx/nota_detalle.php?codigo=5531463&#x00026;fecha=13/07/2018">http://dof.gob.mx/nota_detalle.php?codigo=5531463&#x00026;fecha=13/07/2018</ext-link> (2018) Accessed 20 March 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fenhann, J. CDM Pipeline overview. UNEP-Risoe. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdmpipeline.org/">http://www.cdmpipeline.org/</ext-link> (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CICC. M&#x000e9;xico. Sexta Comunicaci&#x000f3;n Nacional y Segundo Informe Bienal de Actualizaci&#x000f3;n ante la Convenci&#x000f3;n Marco de las Naciones Unidas sobre el Cambio Clim&#x000e1;tico. Comisi&#x000f3;n Intersecretarial de Cambio Clim&#x000e1;tico, Noviembre 2018, Mexico. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://unfccc.int/resource/docs/natc/mexnc5s.pdf">https://unfccc.int/resource/docs/natc/mexnc5s.pdf</ext-link> (2018) Accessed 20 March 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UNFCCC. M&#x000e9;xico y Singapur aceptan la Enmienda de Doha al Protocolo de Kyoto. United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change. Available on line: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://unfccc.int/es/news/mexico-y-singapur-aceptan-la-enmienda-de-doha-al-protocolo-de-kyoto-1">https://unfccc.int/es/news/mexico-y-singapur-aceptan-la-enmienda-de-doha-al-protocolo-de-kyoto-1</ext-link> (2014) Accessed 20th March 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CICC. M&#x000e9;xico. Quinta Comunicaci&#x000f3;n Nacional ante la Convenci&#x000f3;n Marco de las Naciones Unidas sobre el Cambio Clim&#x000e1;tico. Comisi&#x000f3;n Intersecretarial de Cambio Clim&#x000e1;tico, Noviembre 2012, M&#x000e9;xico. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://unfccc.int/resource/docs/natc/mexnc5s.pdf">https://unfccc.int/resource/docs/natc/mexnc5s.pdf</ext-link> Accessed 20 March 2019, (2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">INECC. Evaluaci&#x000f3;n Estrat&#x000e9;gica del Programa Especial de Cambio Clim&#x000e1;tico 2014-2018. Instituto Nacional de Ecolog&#x000ed;a y Cambio Clim&#x000e1;tico, Secretar&#x000ed;a de Medio Ambiente y Recursos Naturales, M&#x000e9;xico. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/261388/Informe__evaluacion_PECC_final_limpio_1_.pdf">https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/261388/Informe__evaluacion_PECC_final_limpio_1_.pdf</ext-link> (2017) Accessed 20 March 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CRE. Aviso para el reporte de Registro Nacional de Emisiones. Factor de emisi&#x000f3;n por consumo de electricidad, 2014. Comisi&#x000f3;n Reguladora de Energ&#x000ed;a, Octubre 2015. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.semarnat.gob.mx/sites/default/files/documentos/cicc/aviso_factor_de_emision_electrico.pdf">http://www.semarnat.gob.mx/sites/default/files/documentos/cicc/aviso_factor_de_emision_electrico.pdf</ext-link> Accessed 20 March, 2019, (2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CRE. Factor de emisi&#x000f3;n del Sector El&#x000e9;ctrico Nacional, 2018. Comisi&#x000f3;n Reguladora de Energ&#x000ed;a, Febrero 2019. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/442910/Aviso_Factor_de_Emisiones_2018.pdf">https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/442910/Aviso_Factor_de_Emisiones_2018.pdf</ext-link> (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">DOF. Presupuesto de Egresos de la Federaci&#x000f3;n para el Ejercicio Fiscal 2012. C&#x000e1;mara de Diputados H. Congreso de la Uni&#x000f3;n, Diario Oficial de la Federaci&#x000f3;n, 27 de Diciembre de 2017, (2011).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">DOF. Presupuesto de Egresos de la Federaci&#x000f3;n para el Ejercicio Fiscal 2006. C&#x000e1;mara de Diputado H. Congreso de la Uni&#x000f3;n, Diario Oficial de la Federaci&#x000f3;n, 22 de Diciembre de 2005, (2005).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">BANXICO. Cotizaci&#x000f3;n de divisas que conforman la canasta del DEG 1/y del DEG respecto al Peso Mexicano 2/ Pesos por Divisa. Sistema de Informaci&#x000f3;n Econ&#x000f3;mica. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.banxico.org.mx/SieInternet/consultarDirectorioInternetAction.do?accion=consultarCuadroAnalitico&#x00026;idCuadro=CA91&#x00026;">http://www.banxico.org.mx/SieInternet/consultarDirectorioInternetAction.do?accion=consultarCuadroAnalitico&#x00026;idCuadro=CA91&#x00026;</ext-link> (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">INEGI. Inflaci&#x000f3;n Hist&#x000f3;rica. Calculadora de Inflaci&#x000f3;n. Instituto Nacional de Estad&#x000ed;stica y Geograf&#x000ed;a, Mexico. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.inegi.org.mx/sistemas/indiceprecios/CalculadoraInflacion.aspx">https://www.inegi.org.mx/sistemas/indiceprecios/CalculadoraInflacion.aspx</ext-link> (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">DOF. Presupuesto de Egresos de la Federaci&#x000f3;n para el Ejercicio Fiscal 2018. C&#x000e1;mara de Diputado H. Congreso de la Uni&#x000f3;n, Diario Oficial de la Federaci&#x000f3;n, 29 de Noviembre de 2017, (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nakhooda, S. and Norman, M. Climate Finance: is it making a difference? Report. (ODI, London, 2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CFU. Climate Funds Update, Overseas Development Institute, Heinrich Boll Stiftung. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://climatefundsupdate.org/">https://climatefundsupdate.org/</ext-link> (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Boykoff, M., and Roberts, T. J. Media coverage of climate change: Current trends, strengths, weaknesses. Human Development Reportn2007/2008 Occassional Paper. (UNDP, 2007).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGregor, J. Three Amigos Summit: What Trudeau, Obama and Pena Nieto agreed on CBC News, 29 June 2016, (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UN. Mexico-President Addresses General, 71st Session, UN Web TV. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://webtv.un.org/watch/mexico-president-addresses-general-debate-71st-session/5133960947001">http://webtv.un.org/watch/mexico-president-addresses-general-debate-71st-session/5133960947001</ext-link> (2016) Accessed 1 June 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">King, E. Patricia Espinosa: Who is the UN&#x02019;s incoming climate change chief? Climate Home News. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.climatechangenews.com/2016/05/05/patricia-espinosa-who-is-the-uns-incoming-climate-change-chief/">https://www.climatechangenews.com/2016/05/05/patricia-espinosa-who-is-the-uns-incoming-climate-change-chief/</ext-link> (2016) Accessed 30th October 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">GOR. I<italic>ntended Nationally Determined Contribution</italic>. (Gobierno de la Rep&#x000fa;blica, M&#x000e9;xico, 2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tests of equality between sets of coefficients in two linear regressions</article-title><source>Econometrica</source><year>1960</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1910133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CPC. Debate presidencial 26 de Abril 2006, Comunicaci&#x000f3;n Pol&#x000ed;tica y Ciudadania. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RTQtE_0kt4I&#x00026;t=25s">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RTQtE_0kt4I&#x00026;t=25s</ext-link>. (2015) Accessed 10 November 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CPC. Debate presidencial 6 de Junio 2006, Comunicaci&#x000f3;n Pol&#x000ed;tica y Ciudadania. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9WOvWxLGVBM&#x00026;t=78s">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9WOvWxLGVBM&#x00026;t=78s</ext-link> (2015) Accessed 10 November 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR94"><label>94.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Reyes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Similarities and contrasts between media coverage and Google web search of &#x0201c;climate change&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;global warming&#x0201d; in Spain</article-title><source>Raz&#x000f3;n y. Palabra</source><year>2015</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>422</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR95"><label>95.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stern, N. et al. <italic>Stern Review: The Economics of Climate Change</italic> (HM Treasury, London, 2006).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR96"><label>96.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vergara-Aceves, J. Acercamiento al nuevo PRI, An&#x000e1;lisis Plural, 2&#x000ba; Semestre de 2012. 127&#x02013;142 (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR97"><label>97.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Boykoff, M., et al. World Newspaper Coverage of Climate Change or Global Warming, 2004-2019. Center for Science and Technology Policy Research, Cooperative Institute for Research in Environmental Sciences, University of Colorado, Media and Climate Change Observatory Data Sets. 10.25810/4c3b-b819 (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR98"><label>98.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Trench, T., Larson, A. M., Libert-Amico A. &#x00026; Ravikumar, A. <italic>Analyzing multilevel governance in Mexico. Lessons for REDD+ from a astudy of land-use change and benefit sharing in Chiapas and Yucat&#x000e1;n, Working Paper 236</italic> (Indonesia Center for International Forestry Research, Bogor, 2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR99"><label>99.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CCMSS. <italic>Presupuesto Forestal 2016 &#x000bf;Nuevos riesgos para los bosques? Monitoreo de Pol&#x000ed;ticas P&#x000fa;blicas</italic> (Nota Informativa 43, Mexico City, 2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR100"><label>100.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sin Embargo. <italic>Elecciones: los temas ausentes</italic> (Sin Embargo, 27 Junio, M&#x000e9;xico, 2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR101"><label>101.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mart&#x000ed;nez, C. <italic>Destaca propuesta ambiental de AMLO</italic> (Mural, 16 Mayo, 2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR102"><label>102.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">GRICCE. Climate Change Laws of the World database, Grantham Research Institute on Climate Change and the Environment and Sabin Center for Climate Change Law. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.lse.ac.uk/GranthamInstitute/legislation/">http://www.lse.ac.uk/GranthamInstitute/legislation/</ext-link> (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR103"><label>103.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Townshed</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>How national legislation can help to solve climate change</article-title><source>Nat. Clim. Change</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nclimate1894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR104"><label>104.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Vedlitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alston</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regional news portrayals of global warming and climate change</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Policy</source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envsci.2008.01.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR105"><label>105.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Scientists&#x02019; views and positions on global warming and climate change: a content analysis of congressional testimonies</article-title><source>Climatic Change</source><year>2015</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10584-015-1390-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR106"><label>106.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">EZPL. Presidencia de la Republica. Sistema Internet de la Presidencia, Administracion 1994-2000, Enrique Zedillo Ponce de Leon. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zedillo.presidencia.gob.mx/">http://zedillo.presidencia.gob.mx/</ext-link> (2000).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR107"><label>107.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">VFQ. Presidencia de la Republica. Administracion 2000-2006, Vicente Fox Quezada. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://fox.presidencia.gob.mx/">http://fox.presidencia.gob.mx/</ext-link> (2006).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR108"><label>108.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">FCH. Presidencia de la Republica. Administracion 2000-2012, Felipe Calderon Hinojosa. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://calderon.presidencia.gob.mx/">http://calderon.presidencia.gob.mx/</ext-link> (2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR109"><label>109.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">EPN. Presidencia de la Republica. Administracion 2012-2018, Enrique Pe&#x000f1;a Nieto. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gob.mx/busqueda?utf8=%E2%9C%93&#x00026;site=presidencia&#x00026;q=">https://www.gob.mx/busqueda?utf8=%E2%9C%93&#x00026;site=presidencia&#x00026;q=</ext-link> (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR110"><label>110.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">AMLO. Administraciones Anteriores. Presidencia de la Rep&#x000fa;blica. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gob.mx/presidencia/acciones-y-programas/administraciones-anteriores">http://www.gob.mx/presidencia/acciones-y-programas/administraciones-anteriores</ext-link> (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR111"><label>111.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirp</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Professionalization as a policy choice</article-title><source>World Politics</source><year>1982</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2010261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR112"><label>112.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Howell, D. C. <italic>Statistical Methods for Psychology</italic>. (Wadsworth CENGE Learning, USA, 2010).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>